Guide to the Marcella Brenner Papers, 1958-2005 MS2304
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Marcella Brenner papers
1958-2005
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Brenner, Marcella
MS2304
7.5 Linear Feet 15 document boxes
Marcella Brenner was a long-tenured member of the George Washington University Community, serving in multiple capacities as a student, professor, program director, trustee, professor emerita, and advisor from 1964 to her death in 2007. Over the course of her long career in higher education, she became one of the foremost experts on museum education and founded the Museum Education Program at George Washington University. In her personal life, she was an avid participat and educator in the DC Jewish community, sponsored and founded philanthropic programs in the US and Israel, and was a lifelong patron of the arts.
Arrangement
Organized into 2 series: George Washington University Files and Personal Files.
Biographical / Historical
Marcella Brenner was born Baltimore and received a two-year diploma in 1929 from Maryland State Teachers College, now Towson University, and an undergraduate degree from Johns Hopkins University in 1934. She taught in the Baltimore public schools from 1930 to 1944, and received a master's degree in sociology from American University in 1949. From 1945 to 1952, she was a writer and editor for the U.S. Public Health Service. Returning to public education, she was a teacher and then principal at Lone Oak Elementary School in Rockville from 1952 to 1964.
In 1964, she received a PhD in Education from George Washington University and subsequently joined the faculty as an instructor. In 1974, she founded the Museum Education Program at George Washington University. She retired as director of the program in 1983 but continued to advise and instruct students in the program until 2007. In 1971, Ms. Brenner founded the Program for Innovative Teaching (the Keren) in Israel, designed to provide individual classroom teachers with funds not normally available to them in the school budget. She also supported the Bezalel Academy of Art and Design in Jerusalem.
She contributed art works by her late husband Morris Louis, the well-known Washington colorist, to museums around the world. She founded the Morris Louis Scholarship to support art students at George Washington University and was a benefactor of the Maryland Institute College of Art, her husband's alma mater. At Jewish Social Services, she taught English to Russian immigrants and established the Brenner Escort Service Fund to transport people to and from doctor's appointments and take notes of the doctor's instructions. An avid reader who loved mystery novels, she was a member of two long-standing book clubs, as well.
Marcella Brenner passed away on Decemeber 25, 2007, in Silver Spring, MD.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marcella Brenner Revocable Trust, 3/26/2012 (2012.037)
Scope and Contents
The materials of this series include correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes, personal notes, educational materials, administrative files, reports, brochures, budgets, proposals, and promotional materials. The materials date from 1958 to 2007 and include those relating to Marcella Brenner's tenure as a student, professor, program director, and trustee at George Washington University, as well as those related to her life away from the University.
Museum administration; Education, Higher -- United States; Museums; Education -- United States -- History; Brenner, Marcella
- George Washington University Files, 1958-2005; 1967-2004; Series 1; 3 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence, memoranda, meeting minutes, personal notes, educational materials, and administrative files. The materials date from 1958 to 2005 and include those relating to Marcella Brenner's tenure as a student, professor, program director, and trustee at George Washington University.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged into three subseries: Museum Education Program, Academic Files, and Board of Trustees.
  - Museum Education Program, 1978-2004; Series 1 Subseries 1; 0.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains materials related to the Museum Education Program, founded by Marcella Brenner at George Washington University in 1974.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - The Humanities, Education, and Working, 1978; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Brenner Endowment, 1987-1993; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Proposed Consolidation of Museum Programs, 1991; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Museum Education Newsletters, 1991-1995; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brenner Endowment, 1992-1997; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Opening Graduate School of Education & Human Development Building, 2004; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Museum Education Program Students, 2004; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Museum Education Program Poster, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Academic Files, 1958-2005; Series 1 Subseries 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains Marcella Brenner's personal files used for supporting her teaching activites over the course of her career at George Washington University. Includes subject files, papers, personal notes,
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Adults - ICOM, 1982; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Appointments and Salary, 1964-1981; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Aristotle - Lavine, 1977; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Art Books for Children, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Art Issues, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - As I Look About Me, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Class Log Sample, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Cloudy Concepts, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cloudy Concepts at the School Level, 1959; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Control Techniques, 1958; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Cooperative Learning, 1988; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Creative Teaching Literature, December 1966; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Creative Writing, 1959; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Creativity, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Demands of Teaching, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Doctor of Education Degree, 1961-1964; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - English 62 - Comedy, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - English 172 - The Bible as Literature, 1991; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Evaluation Leadership, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Faculty Senate Special Committee on Professor Linda DePauw, 2001; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Helping Relationship, 1960; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - History Museums, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - ICOM, 1975-1976; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Interview Arts and Skills, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Interview - Intervention, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Interview - Obermeier, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Irvington Publishers, 1985-1990; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Joshua Taylor, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Leadership, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Lilith-Sterling, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Loser", undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Marcella - Professional, 1969-1987; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Michael J. Lane, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Naipul, 1979; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Oral History - French, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Personality Development, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Personnel - Petersen, 1982; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Photographs, 2005; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Planning for Teaching, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Psychology Principles, 1968; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Redl - New Culture, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Sachar - Modern Jewish History, Spring 1979; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Student Paper (Education 123), undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Supervision, Parent-Teacher Interview, 1962; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Tuckman-Folly, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - The Slow Learner - Opportunities for Creativity, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Real Interview Techniques in a School Setting, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Slow Learner Contradictions, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Walt Disney Accused, 1965; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Why Children Misbehave, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Board of Trustees, 1987-2001; Series 1 Subseries 3; 1 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains materials relating to Dr. Brenner's term on the George Washington University Board of Trustees.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Materials in this series are restricted for 50 years from the date of creation and thus may be unavailable for access. Please contact the Special Collections Research Center staff for further information.
    - Board of Trustees Reappointment, 1987-1993; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Board of Trustees Committee on Academic Affairs Meeting [1/2], 14 May 1998; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Board of Trustees Committee on Academic Affairs Meeting [2/2], 14 May 1998; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Board of Trustees Committee on Academic Affairs, 2001; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Board of Trustees Academic Affairs and Finance Committees [1/2], 2001; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Board of Trustees Academic Affairs and Finance Committees [2/2], 2001; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Board of Trustees Academic Affairs and Finance Committees [2/2], 2001; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Board of Trustees Meeting [1/3], 17-18 May 2001; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Board of Trustees Meeting [2/3], 17-18 May 2001; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Board of Trustees Meeting [3/3], 17-18 May 2001; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Personal Files, 1967-2007; 1967-2004; Series 2; 4.5 Linear Feet
  Organized into three subseries: Jewish Education Materials, Philanthropy, and the Program for Innovative Teaching.
  The materials of this series include correspondence, reports, memoranda, notes, brochures, educational materials, budgets, proposals, and promotional materials. They range in date from 1967 to 2007 and include Marcella Brenner's collection of personal files not related to her work with George Washington University.
  - Jewish Education Materials, 1967-2007; Series 2 Subseries 1; 1.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains materials used and collected by Marcella Brenner in the course of her teaching English and other subjects through Jewish Social Services.
    - Afrikomen Question Map, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Adas Israel Congregation, Rescue in Denmark, 1998-1999; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Adas Israel Officers, 2001; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Bible Class, 1981; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Bible Selections, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Bible Study, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Class: Capturing the Zeitgeist, 1993; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - DC Metro Area Judaica Shops, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - English, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - From Perestroyka to Bar Mitzvah, 2004; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Holidays, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Jewish Education, 1996; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Jewish Historical Society Penny Postcard Project, 2003; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Jospe, 1980; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Material Used in Teaching Russians, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Jewish Education Materials, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Monday Book Club, 1983-2007; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Music, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Passover Workshop, 2003; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Proportion in Fiction, 1989; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Rescue in Denmark Program, 2000; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Saltis, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Sunday Book Club, 1967-2002; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - To Do for Class, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Timelines of Jewish History, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Tu Bshvat, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Teaching Bible Studies, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Seder 2003, Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Teaching the Russians, 2003; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Women's Memoirs - Beth El Class, 2001; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Philanthropy, 1976-2007; Series 2 Subseries 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains materials related to Marcella Brenner's philanthropic activities over the course of her life.
    - First Appearance in an Israeli Professional Publication, Alisa Fuss, 1976; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Israel Endowment Funds Annual Reports, 1978-1998; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Moshav Edan, 1981; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1983; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Lee Oestreicher, 1984; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - John Horrworth Children's Literature Collection Endowment, 1989; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - New Orleans Museum of Art: Passionate Visions of the American South, 1991; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - The Mofet Institute, 1998; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - B'nai B'nth Museum, 1999; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Morris Louis Scholarships, 2000-2004; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Proposal for Marcella Brenner Center for Museum Educators, 2001; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - MICA, 2001-2003; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Trip to Israel 2003, Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Trip to Israel 2004, Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Israel, May 2004, Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Interests outside the Kerem, 2005; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Belazel, 2005-2006; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Project Interchange Domestic Seminars, 2005-2006; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Israel Trip 2006, Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Maryland Institute of College Art, 2007; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Buy Israeli Productions, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - George Washington Scholarships, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Philanthropy Materials, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Program for Innovative Teaching, 1977-2005; Series 2 Subseries 3; 1.5 Linear Feet
    This subseries contains materials related to the founding and continued development of the Program for Innovative Teaching, founded by Marcella Brenner.
    - Project Reports '77/'78 - '78/'79, 1977-1979; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Application Forms, 1981-1982; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Project Reports, 1986-1989; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Teaching, Learning - JSSA Mobile University, 1988-1990; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Project Reports, 1990-1994; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 30th Anniversary Tribute, 1991; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Budget, 2003; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Proposals [1/5], 2000-2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Proposals [2/5], 2000-2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Proposals [3/5], 2000-2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Proposals [4/5], 2000-2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Proposals [5/5], 2000-2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Proposals for Projects [1/2], 2005; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Proposals for Projects [2/2], 2005; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Proposals and Reviews (Teacher Innovation) [1/2], 2005; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Proposals and Reviews (Teacher Innovation) [2/2], 2005; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Publications [1/2], undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Publications [2/2], undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Promotional Materials, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 12, Folder 7)